Guide to the M.D. Ball Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
M. D. Ball papers
1868-1927
WA MSS S-2359
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.09
(2 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The papers consist primarily of scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, manuscript notes, and Congressional bills regarding Alaska, but also include correspondence, customs documents, writings, maps, and a few photographs and printed illustrations. They document Ball's work as Customs Collector in Sitka at a time when that office was the chief representative of the U. S. government in Alaska; his term as Alaska's first delegate to Congress, 1882-85, and his campaign for representation and governance for the Territory; and other events in Alaskan history to 1887. Particularly well documented are the events of the winter of 1878-79, when U. S. citizens in Sitka appealed to a British warship for protection from native tribes. Ball's correspondence includes letters from Benjamin Harrison, William Dall, M. P. Deady, E. P. Lull, Marcus Baker, and John H. Mitchell, as well as from the Pacific Coast Steamship Company regarding his writing for their pamphlet "All About Alaska." The papers also include letters to Ball's daughter from James Wickersham, a 1927 blueprint for the Alaska flag, several printed and manuscript maps of Alaska, a manuscript map showing military operations of the Crimean War, and two photographs of St. Peter's by the Sea, a church in Sitka.
Ball, M. D. (Mottrom Dulany), 1835-1887
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Edward Eberstadt and Sons on the William Robertson Coe Western Americana Fund, 1957.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Mottrom Dulany Ball (1835-1887) was born in Fairfax County, Virginia, and was educated at the College of William and Mary. He taught school until the outbreak of the Civil War, when he formed a cavalry company and rose to the rank of Colonel in the Confederate Army. After the war, he practiced law and founded the Virginia Sentinel, which folded in 1876. In January 1878, he was appointed Collector of Customs for Alaska, and moved to Sitka with his wife, Sallie Lewis Wright Ball, and children. In September of 1881, he was elected Alaska's first unofficial delegate to Congress. Ball served as U. S. District Attorney for Alaska from 1885 to 1887, and was the founding editor of the Alaskan, a Sitka newspaper.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist primarily of scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, manuscript notes, and Congressional bills regarding Alaska, but also include correspondence, customs documents, writings, maps, and a few photographs and printed illustrations. They document Ball's work as Customs Collector in Sitka at a time when that office was the chief representative of the U. S. Government in Alaska; his term as Alaska's first delegate to Congress, 1882-1885, and his campaign for representation and governance for the Territory; and other events in Alaskan history to 1887.
Series I, Correspondence, includes letters to Ball from Benjamin Harrison, William Dall, M. P. Deady, E. P. Lull, Marcus Baker of the USGS, and John H. Mitchell, as well as from the Pacific Steamship Company regarding his writing for their pamphlet "All About Alaska." Also present are letters to Ball's daughter from James Wickersham.
Series II, Papers, is organized in two subseries, Documents and Writings. Documents include customs receipts from 1877 to 1879, petitions for Ball's election as delegate to Congress, printed bills and statements by Ball to Congress, a subscription for the 1880 4th of July celebration in Sitka, and a report on mining in Cook's Inlet in 1898 by B. Frank Hand. Writings consists of two draft chapters from a larger work about Alaska culture and history, a prospectus about travel in Alaska written for tourists, and a draft article about mining.
Series III, Scrapbooks, consists of two bound scrapbooks and two loose pages from a third volume. The scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings, manuscript notes, congressional bills, and printed maps. The first volume, in Folder 21, largely concerns the events of the winter of 1878-1879, when U. S. citizens in Sitka appealed to a British warship for protection from native tribes, and the ensuing controversy.
Series IV, Visual Material, consists of a 1927 Blueprint for the Alaska flag, several printed and manuscript maps of Alaska, a manuscript map showing military operations of the Crimean war, two photographs of St. Peter's by the SEa, a church in Sitka, and two lithographs removed from a Russian book, one of them showing the Sitka harbor.
Crimean War, 1853-1856 -- Maps; Flags -- Alaska; Indians of North America -- Alcohol use -- Alaska; Indians of North America -- Alaska -- Government relations; Indians of North America -- Alaska; Proportional representation -- Alaska; Representative government and representation -- Alaska; Alaska -- Description and travel; Alaska -- History -- 1867-1959; Alaska -- Politics and government -- 1867-1959; Sitka (Alaska); Clippings (information artifacts); Maps (documents); Photographic prints; Territorial records; Politicians -- Alaska; Baker, Marcus, 1849-1903; Ball, M. D. (Mottrom Dulany), 1835-1887; Dall, William Healey, 1845-1927; Deady, Matthew P. (Matthew Paul), 1824-1893; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901; Lull, Edward Phelps, 1836-1887; Mitchell, John H. (John Hipple), 1835-1905; Wickersham, James, 1857-1939; Pacific Coast Steamship Company
- Correspondence, 1879-1925; Series I; 12 folders (.08 linear feet)
  - TO M. D. BALL
    - Beardslee, Captain, U.S.S. Jamestown, Sitka, 1879 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Brown, George, U.S.S. Alaska, Sitka, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Butler, M. C., Washington, D.C., 1880 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dall, William H., Washington, D.C., 1886 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deady, Matthew P., Portland, Oregon, 1881 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Goodall Perkins & Co. (Pacific Coast Steamship Company), San Francisco, 1886 Jun 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Harrison, Benjamin, Washington, D.C., 1885-86 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lull, Edward P., U.S.S. Wachusett, Sitka, 1881 Oct 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mitchell, John H., Washington, D.C., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - United States Geological Survey, Marcus Baker, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - OTHER LETTERS
    - de St. Marceaux & Co., Reims, to Monsieur le Consul de France, Nouv. Arkhangel [Sitka], 1880 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Wickersham, James, Juneau, to Sallie Lewis Ball [daughter of MDB], Washington, D.C., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Papers, 1877-98; Series II; 8 folders (.08 linear feet)
  - DOCUMENTS
    - Customs receipts and orders, 1877-79 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Subscription for 4th of July celebration at Sitka, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Petitions and ratifications of the election of MDB to represent Alaska at the 47th Congress, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Printed bills, statements and reports by MDB to the 47th Congress, 1882-83 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Typescript carbon, corrected, of report about mining in Cook's Inlet by B. Frank Hand, mining engineer, [1898] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - WRITINGS
    - "Illustrative Stories" and "Slavery and Witchcraft," manuscript chapters from a larger work (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Prospectus: The Great North West," manuscript and typescript (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Article on mining, manuscript draft, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Scrapbooks, 1868-87; Series III; 5 folders (.21 linear feet)
  - Volume containing manuscript notes and clippings regarding Alaska's history, culture, and resources, 1868-80 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a detailed account (p. 67) of MDB's actions as Customs Collector 1878-79; many of the clippings concern Sitka's appeal to a British warship for protection from native tribes in February 1879, and its aftermath
  - Loose clippings removed from pages 96-97 of above volume, [ca. 1880s] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Loose clippings removed from pages 96-97 of above volume, 1886-87, n.d.
  - Loose clippings removed from pages 102-103 of above volume, 1885, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Loose clippings removed from pages 102-103 of above volume, 1886-87, n.d.
  - Bound volume titled "M. D. Ball/ Sketch-Book," containing clippings and maps, 1874-86 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes biographical article and portrait of MDB, 1882; clippings from the Alaska Herald 1874, Presbyterian Home Missionary [ca. 1885?] and Congressional Record for 1886; a census of the School Population of Southeastern Alaska 1885-86; other loose items; two maps tipped in at the back of the volume
  - Two loose pages of clippings regarding the need for Territorial government and representation in Congress for Alaska, 1881-84 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Visual Material, 1878-1927; Series IV; 4 folders (.04 linear feet)
  - MAPS
    - Printed map of Alaska showing timber, tundra, and glaciers, from the tenth census of the United States, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Manuscript map showing currents flowing down the West coast of North America (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Printed map, "Route of the Military Reconnaissance of 1883," with manuscript annotations by MDB, [1886]
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Box 1, folder 24
    - Printed map, "Alaska and Adjoining Region" [to the West]
    - Manuscript map, on cloth, of Tchitchagoff and Baranoff Islands and Chatham Strait, Alaska (fragment)
    - Manuscript map, on cloth, of Chatham Strait, Prince Frederick Sound, and nearby islands, Alaska (fragment)
    - Manuscript map of the Crimea, showing Sevastopol, Balaclava, and military positions in the area, ca. 1855, [ca. 1878?]
  - OTHER VISUAL MATERIAL
    - 2 photographs of St. Peter's by the Sea, Sitka, one interior and one exterior view (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 2 lithographs from a Russian book, one showing Sitka's harbor, the other a portrait of Alexander [Taranov?] (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Blueprint, "The Official Flag of Alaska, Adopted May 2, 1927," with swatch of blue silk, 1927 May
- Oversize, 5 folders (1.67 linear feet)
  - Clippings removed from pages 96-97 of scrapbook in folder 21, 1886-87, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Clippings removed from pages 102-103 of scrapbook in folder 21, 1886-87, n.d. (Box bsd, folder 31)
  - Two maps of Chatham Strait, Baranoff Island, and nearby region (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Map of the Crimea ca. 1855, [ca. 1878?] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Blueprint for Flag of Alaska, 1927 May (Box 2, Folder 34)